<litprog>
<object name="browse.c" language="c" item="browse_main"/>


<format name="index">
<html><head><title>Folder browser CGI</title></head>
<body>
<h2>A permission-based folder browser CGI</h2>
<center>
[ <a href="wftk_user.zip">download</a> ] [ <a href="browser.xml">xml source</a> ]
[ <a href="http://www.vivtek.com/wftk/discuss.pl">wftk discussion</a> ]
</center>

<hr/>
This browser is based on the <a href=index.html>user module for wftk</a> and is distributed as a part of
that code.  It allows hierarchical data to be browsed very easily, and additional objects to be added
to a hierarchy.  Moreover, the user module allows a given user's view of the hierarchy to be affected by
that user's permission levels for various objects and groups of objects.
<p/>
The browser is implemented as a CGI program.  Since display of a fully opened folder tree thus requires a full
traversal of that tree on every request, an alternative which caches some results in persistent storage might
be a nice extension at some point, but in the meantime this will serve many purposes.  Not only can it be used
to browse users themselves for an admin tool, it can also be pressed into service for menu maintenance for the
overall wftk user interface, it can organize groups of procdefs for the PDM, and so on.  Basically it should
do a good job allowing a user to traverse any kind of hierarchical structure, especially where that structure
depends on the access level of the user.
<p/>
The whole thing is defined in a single file, browse.c, which compiles to the CGI executable in question.
The CGI interface is managed by <a href="http://www.vivtek.com/xml/xmlapi/xmlcgi.html">XMLCGI</a>, which is
an optional part of the <a href="http://www.vivtek.com/xml/xmlapi/">XMLAPI</a>.  You'll be seeing lots of the
XMLAPI around this project.
<p/>
Table of contents:
[##itemlist##]

<center>
<hr width="75%"/>
<table width="75%"><tr><td><font size="-1">
This code and documentation are released under the terms of the GNU license.  They are
copyright (c) 2000, Vivtek.  All rights reserved except those explicitly
granted under the terms of the GNU license.  This presentation was prepared using
<a href="http://www.vivtek.com/lpml/">LPML</a>.  Try literate programming.  You'll like it.
</font>
</td>
</tr>
</table>
</center>
</body></html>
</format>

<format name="default">
<html><head><title>Browser:: [##label##]</title></head>
<body>
<h2>[##label##]</h2>
<center>
[<nbsp/><a href="[##prev##]">Previous: [##prevlabel##]</a><nbsp/>]
[<nbsp/><a href="browse.html">Top: [##indexlabel##]</a><nbsp/>]
[<nbsp/><a href="[##next##]">Next: [##nextlabel##]</a><nbsp/>]
</center>

<hr/>
[##body##]


<center>
[<nbsp/><a href="[##prev##]">Previous: [##prevlabel##]</a><nbsp/>]
[<nbsp/><a href="browse.html">Top: [##indexlabel##]</a><nbsp/>]
[<nbsp/><a href="[##next##]">Next: [##nextlabel##]</a><nbsp/>]
<br/><br/><hr width="75%"/>
<table width="75%"><tr><td><font size="-1">
This code and documentation are released under the terms of the GNU license.  They are
copyright (c) 2000, Vivtek.  All rights reserved except those explicitly
granted under the terms of the GNU license.
</font></td></tr></table>
</center>
</body></html>
</format>

<item name="browse" label="Folder browser" format="index">
</item>

<item name="browse_main" label="user.c: implementation">
First off is our includes.  Note that local wftk includes are in the parent directory; we're compiling browse.c out of
the user module directory.  The <code>localdefs.h</code> file contains definitions local to the current installation;
under Unix that typically includes the location of the various repositories (of which we need two), but under Windows
that is taken care of in the Registry.  However, the ending for CGI programs is also included in <code>localdefs.h</code>.
<piece>
#include <stdio.h>
#include <string.h>
#include <stdlib.h>
#include "user.h"
#include "xmlcgi.h"
#include "../localdefs.h"

/* ------------------------------------------------------------------ */
/* browse.c                                                           */
/* A CGI program for folder-oriented, permission-based hierarchical   */
/* browsing.  This program is part of the wftk workflow toolkit and   */
/* is distributed under the terms of the GNU license.                 */
/* Copyright (c) 2000, Vivtek: wftk@vivtek.com                        */
/* ------------------------------------------------------------------ */
</piece>

<piece>
XML * cgi;
XML * environment;
XML * input;

XML * current_user;

int main (int argc, char * argv[])
{
   cgi = cgi_init ();
   environment = xml_loc (cgi, "cgicall.environment");
   input = xml_loc (cgi, "cgicall.query");

   current_user = user_authenticate (environment, AUTH_DOMAIN);
   if (!current_user) {
      printf ("[[html>[[head>[[title>User authentication required[[/title>[[/head>\n");
      printf ("[[body>[[h2>User authentication required [[/h2>[[hr>\n");
      printf ("A valid user authentication response is required to access this area.\n");
      printf ("[[/body>[[/html>\n");
      exit(0);
   }

   printf ("Content-Type: text/plain\n\n");
   xml_write (stdout, cgi);
}
</piece>
</item>


</litprog>
